Finding Aid for Paul G. Kauper papers, 1925-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Paul G. Kauper papers 1925-1974
Kauper, Paul G.
85306 Aa 2
Professor of law at the University of Michigan. Papers include correspondence, course materials, and professional files reflecting his interest in constitutional law, university affairs, and legal questions of religious liberty and church-state relations; and manuscripts of writings, speech and conference files, reprints and copies of articles, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
42 linear feet
The collection was the gift of Professor Kauper and his family. Donor no. 5383
The collection is open to research.
Paul G. Kauper was born in Richmond, Indiana. He earned his undergraduate degree at Earlham College in 1929 and a law degree from the University of Michigan in 1932. After graduating he served a s a research assistant at the Law School until 1934 when he joined the firm of white and Case in New York city as a junior associate. In 1936 he returned to the University of Michigan as an assistant professor and in 1939 was promoted to associate professor.
From 1942 to 1945 he was on leave as attorney for the Pan American Petroleum and Transport company. after his return he was promoted to full professor in 1946. Kauper was named the Henry M. Butzel Professor of Law in May 1965
Kauper was a nationally recognized authority on constitutional, particularly in the areas of civil liberties and church-stale relations. He was an advisor to the Michigan Constitutional Convention of 1961-1962.
Kauper died May 22, 1974.
The Paul G. Kauper his teaching and research as a member of the Law School faculty, professional activities and community service on various commission and committees. Basic biographical information can be found in the Topical File in box 17.
The papers include correspondence, course materials, and professional files reflecting his interest in constitutional law, university affairs, and legal questions of religious liberty and church-state relations; and manuscripts of writings, speech and conference files, reprints and copies of articles, and photographs.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor Citizens' Council.; Church and state.; Kauper, Paul G.; Law.; Lutheran Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; State Bar of Michigan.; Michigan. Governor's Transportation Study Commission (1950-1952); Transportation--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; Zion Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Public schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Trucking--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Kauper, Paul G.; Photographs.; University of Heidelberg.; University of Michigan--Law School--Faculty.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Kauper, Paul G.; Church and state--United States.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Religion.
Genre Terms:
Compact discs.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence 1925-1974
  The Correspondence file is arranged chronologically.
  - 1925-1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1956 (Box 2)
  - 1957-1963 (Box 3)
  - 1964-1968 (Box 4)
  - 1969-1974 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with publishers (Box 6)
- University course materials
  The University course material (box 7-11 and 33-35) include outlines and lecture notes for courses in constitutional law, municipal corporations, property, taxation, and a Church-State seminar.
  - Constitutional Law (Box 7)
  - Constitutional Law (Box 8)
  - Constitutional Law (Box 9)
  - Municipal Corporations (Box 9)
  - Comparative Constitutional Law (Box 10)
  - Church State Seminar (Box 11)
  - Federal Income Taxation (Box 11)
- Topical Files
  The series Topical Files is somewhat haphazardly arranged. It includes Law School and general University of Michigan material, files related to his professional activities, and biographical files.
  - Order of the COIF (Box 12)
  - American Association of Law Schools: Curriculum Committee (Box 12)
  - U of M Law School Curriculum Committee (Box 12)
  - Institute of Public Administration (Box 13)
  - Lutheran Church in America activities (Box 13)
  - Ann Arbor. Zion Lutheran Church (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan
    - Honorary Degrees Committee (Box 14)
    - Distinguished Faculty Awards Committee (Box 14)
    - Planning Committee (Box 14)
    - Development Committee (Box 14)
    - Building Committee (Box 14)
    - Fulbright Grant Evaluation Committee (Box 15)
    - University of Michigan Law School: Committee on Graduate and Research work (Box 15)
    - University Musical Society (Box 15)
    - Law School: Administrative Communications (Box 15)
    - Committee on Year-Round Operations (Box 15)
  - Michigan State Bar Committee on Constitutional Law (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan (Box 16)
    - Student Religious Association (Box 16)
    - Interfaith Center (Box 16)
    - Office of Religious Affairs (Box 16)
    - Committee on Studies in Religion (Box 16)
  - American Association of Law Schools: Committee on Academic Freedom and Tenure (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Grading Standards and Graduation Requirements (Box 16)
    - Senate By-Laws Committee (1954) (Box 16)
    - Law School Committee on Evaluation of Faculty Services 1940 (Box 16)
  - Biographical material
    - Bibliographical material (Box 17)
    - Personal memorabilia 1929-1967 (Box 17)
      (intended as scrapbook; includes programs, clippings, etc.)
  - University of Michigan.
    - Committee on Taxation 1951-1955 (Box 17)
    - Law School Library Advisory Committee (Box 17)
    - Law School: Committee on Tenure Procedures (Box 17)
    - Law School Summer Institute (Taxation) of Business Enterprise) 1951 (Box 17)
    - Phoenix Project Faculty Committee. (Box 17)
  - Visiting Professor, University of Arizona (Box 17)
  - Earlham College Alumni matters (Box 17)
  - Lutheran Educational Conference of North America: Commission on the Future (Box 18)
  - Proposed Journal on Law Reform (University of Michigan) (Box 18)
  - Heidelberg University: Honorary Degree 1970 (Box 18)
  - Michigan Constitutional Convention 1962 (Box 18)
  - Legal memoranda and private case material 1930 (Box 18)
  - Wayne County Law Practice 1931-1932 (Box 18)
  - New York State Bar Examinations course 1935 (Box 18)
  - Motor carrier transport cases (Box 18)
  - Committee on Education for Professional Responsibility (Box 19)
  - Ann Arbor Fair Housing Ordinance (Box 19)
  - Michigan Civil Rights Commission (Box 19)
  - Federal Civil Rights Legislation (Box 19)
  - Proposed Commission on Religion and Public Education (Box 19)
  - University of Michigan. Faculty Committee on Teaching Methods (Box 19)
  - University of Michigan. Law School: Editorial Committee (Box 19)
  - Michigan Aid to Dependent Children of Unemployed Act (Box 19)
  - Federal legislation to limit state taxing power (Box 19)
  - Michigan State College name change (Box 19)
  - Clardy Committee investigating University of Michigan faculty (Box 19)
  - Taxation materials and cases (Box 19)
  - University of Michigan. Law School Case Clubs (Box 19)
  - University of Michigan. Committee for Referral (Box 19)
  - Constitutional Law: Miscellaneous clippings, speeches, etc. (Box 19)
  - Lobbying Act Amendments 1955-1957 (Box 19)
  - American Enterprise Institute (Box 19)
  - Proposal to establish Federal Voting Age Standard (Box 19)
  - Proposal regarding teaching of creation in public schools (Box 19)
  - Proposal regarding tax credits for private school payment (Box 19)
  - Proposal regarding property tax and education financing (Box 19)
  - Campus demonstrators 1960s (Box 19)
  - Proposal to Limit Habeus Corpus as Post-Conviction remedy, 1972. (Box 19)
  - Committee on Academic Standards and Incentives 1969-1970 (Box 19)
  - American Association of Law Schools: Orientation Program in American Law (Box 20)
  - University of Michigan
    - Law School Round Table Programs (Box 20)
    - Calendar Revision 1967 (Box 20)
    - War Lectures Committee (Box 20)
  - State Board of Education (Powers of) (Box 20)
  - University of Michigan. Law School: Special Admissions Policy (Box 20)
  - U.S. Senate Committee on Termination of National Emergency (Box 20)
  - A.A.L.S.: Committee on Supreme Court Decisions 1967-1968 (Box 20)
  - Limiting the powers of the President (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Comparative Law materials (Box 21)
  - Reprints and copies of articles (Box 21)
  - Topical files concerning Lutheran Church and church-state legal matters (Box 22)
  - Topical files concerning Lutheran Church and church-state legal matters (Box 23)
    (continued)
  - Topical files concerning Lutheran Church and church-state legal matters (Box 24)
  - Topical files concerning Lutheran Church and church-state legal matters (Box 25)
  - Topical files concerning Lutheran Church and church-state legal matters (Box 26)
- Speech and Writing Files
  The Speech and Writings files (not fully processed) includes file on speaking engagements and professional conferences and manuscripts of Kauper's writings and Book reviews.
  - Speech and conference files (Box 27)
  - Speech and conference files (Box 28)
  - Manuscripts of writings (Box 29)
  - Manuscripts of writings (Box 30)
  - Book reviews (Box 30)
- Commissions and Committees
  The Commissions and Committees series (2 linear ft.) consists of correspondence, reports and other material relating Kauper's public service. Most notable are the Ann Arbor School Board's Special Committee to Study Racial Discrimination in the Public Schools, 1963-1964 and the Michigan State Bar Association, Condemnation Procedure Committee, 1956-1969.
  - Governor's Transportation Study Commission 1950-1952
    - General correspondence, reports, recommendations, and membership (Box 31)
  - Ann Arbor Citizens' Council, Executive Board 1955-1957 (Box 31)
  - Ann Arbor School Board's Special Committee to Study Racial Discrimination in the Public Schools 1963-1964
    - Drafts and final reports (Box 31)
    - Memoranda (Box 31)
    - Newspaper and magazine clippings (Box 31)
    - Official notices, agenda, and minutes of meetings (Box 31)
    - Reports of testimony (Box 31)
    - Personal notes (Box 31)
  - Michigan State Bar Association, Condemnation Procedure Committee 1956-1969
    - Reports (Box 32)
    - Correspondence and notes (Box 32)
    - Miscellaneous matters (Box 32)
- University Course Materials, ca. 1949-1974
  - Church and State Seminar
    - 1962-1963 (Box 33)
    - 1971 (Box 33)
    - 1972 (Box 33)
    - 1973 (Box 33)
  - Comparative Constitutional Law Seminar
    - Spring 1956 (Box 33)
    - Spring 1962 (Box 33)
    - Spring 1963 (Box 33)
    - Winter 1968 (Box 33)
    - Fall 1968 (Box 33)
    - Winter 1970 (Box 33)
    - Fall 1970 (Box 33)
    - Winter 1972, 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Winter 1973 (Box 33)
    - Winter 1974 (Box 33)
  - Constitutional Law
    - Notes I-A, 2 folders (Box 34)
    - Notes I-B, 3 folders (Box 34)
    - Notes II-A, 2 folders (Box 34)
    - Old Notes-Part 11, 4 folders (Box 34)
    - Outlines 1952 (Box 34)
    - Seminar, Spring 1949 (Box 34)
  - Municipal Corporations-I (Box 34)
    - Outline (Box 34)
    - Notes-Chapters 1-3 (Box 34)
    - Notes-Vol. II (Box 34)
    - Municipal Contracts (Box 34)
    - Municipal Funds (Box 34)
    - Municipal Indebtedness (Box 35)
    - Municipal Tort Liability (Box 35)
  - Property (date unknown)
    - Outline (Box 35)
    - Notes, 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Taxation-I
    - Outline, 4 folders (Box 35)
    - Outline 1955, 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 35)
  - Taxation-II
    - Spring 1952 (Box 35)
    - Summer 1953, 2 folders (Box 35)
- Correspondence
  - 1967 (Box 35)
  - 1974 (Box 35)
- Writings
  - OPAL (drafts of panel discussions) 1965, undated (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, (dates unknown)
    - "The Clayton Act-Section 5" (Box 35)
    - "The Clayton Act-Amendment 7 it (Box 35)
    - "The Permissible Scope of FTC.... (Box 35)
    - "Possible Laws vs. Moral and Religious Laws (Box 35)
  - Reprints, (dates unknown)
    - "Civil Right-Current Perspective" (Box 35)
    - "Constitutionalization of Criminal Procedure" (Box 35)
    - "Legislative Department-Article No. 1" (Box 35)
    - "Liberty of Mind" (Box 35)
- Diaries
  - 1923-1934 1939-1940 (Box 36)
  - 1943-1973 (Box 37)
- Addresses, Speeches
  - 1930s-1960s (Box 37)
    (unprocessed)
- Chronological files
  (correspondence and scrapbook materials interspersed)
  - 1930-1956 (Box 38)
  - 1957-1963 (Box 39)
  - 1964-1971 (Box 40)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 41)
- Lutheran Church
  - University of Michigan Lutheran Student Association (Box 41)
  - Zion Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) (Box 41)
- Publications
  - 1940s-1970s (Box 42)
- Sound Recordings
  The sound recordings (audiotape and CD) consist of a series of lectures on church-state relations given to a group assembled at the Lutheran student chapel in Ann Arbor, February-April 1963.
  - Lecture series on church-state relations 1963
    - audio tapes, 2 tapes (Box 42)
    - CD copies of tapes, 10 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 42)
- Photographs (Box 42)
  The Photographs series includes portraits; and photographs of Kauper and his wife at Heidelberg University, where Kauper received an honorary degree in 1970.